<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: statistics | Shoestring Psycholing]]></title>
  <link href="http://shoestringpsycholing.github.com/blog/categories/statistics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shoestringpsycholing.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-05T22:57:11-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://shoestringpsycholing.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Scott Jackson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kruschke Chapter 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://shoestringpsycholing.github.com/blog/2012/11/05/kruschke-chapter-3/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-05T22:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://shoestringpsycholing.github.com/blog/2012/11/05/kruschke-chapter-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the first really substantial chapter; the first two were really just a warm-up. Kruschke presents this chapter as a kind of intro to probability, but (naturally) he makes some very specific choices about what to approach and how to approach it.  A lot of it comes across as kind of foreshadowing, which makes it a little hard to follow or grasp the point of at times. Ultimately, I think this chapter should go pretty quick the first read-through, to prime some ideas, but the ideas probably won't really start to sink in until they get applied later.</p>

<p>Another overall comment: Kruschke points this out at some point himself, but the fact is that throughout this chapter, he's really talking about two kinds (or contexts) of probability. One is as a mathematical expression of belief, which, I assume, is pretty much a given for any kind of Bayesian analysis.  The other is the parameter (&theta;) of interest that one is trying to estimate.  I mean, in all the coin-flipping examples, there is the probability of heads, which is just a parameter of the data-generating process.  In a different kind of data or analysis, it might be something else, not probability (I'm guessing that when we get to Bayesian regression, the parameter will be something like a regression coefficient, which is not a probability). And then there's the probability (or belief) in a parameter value (<em>p</em>(&theta;)), which is always going to be expressed as probability (e.g., for regression, there should be probabilities/beliefs for different coefficient values).  As intuitive and appealing as the coin-flipping examples are, I find this double-sided discussion of probability to be kind of confusing.</p>

<p>So, on to the details of the chapter. Kruschke focuses on the simple case of predicting coin flips and deciding whether the coin is fair.  This has the advantage of not only being conceptually intuitive, but also numerically convenient, allowing for a variety of analytic approaches that don't require the heavier-duty computational tools of MCMC, and I'm sure this was a choice Kruschke made by design.</p>

<p>But illustrating my quibble above, he starts with a discussion about how the fairness of the coin (the parameter &theta;) is a probability, and this can be simulated as a long-run relative frequency, or derived mathematically, and then he switches abruptly to a brief discussion about probability as a expression of subjective belief, even discussing how one might heuristically estimate one's own internal numerical belief in something. I find this back-and-forth discussion a little disorienting, and paradoxically, it feels like he goes into too much detail and not enough detail. The discussion of "calibrating" one's subjective belief seems to invite more questions and confusions than are necessary to make the simple point that in Bayesian analysis, "belief" is represented mathematically by probabilities. But it's not quite in-depth enough to foster a deep understanding or exploration of the ideas.</p>

<p>I think if I were using this for a course, I would want to <em>either</em> (a) spend more time on fleshing out the ideas in this chapter, and take care to very explicitly pull apart the concepts of probability-as-parameter vs. probability-as-belief, or (b) speed through or defer sections of the chapter entirely, jump straight into some analysis, and refer back to sections in this chapter to help present the basic ideas behind the analysis.</p>

<p>Working through the rest of the chapter, I feel like he's foreshadowing the steps from Chapters 5 through 7, from a purely analytic approach, to a grid approximation, to MCMC sampling.  He touches on a number of interesting points, including some nice discussions of:</p>

<ul>
<li>probability distributions (<em>mass</em> for discrete outcomes and <em>density</em> for continuous)</li>
<li>the normal probability distribution</li>
<li>the relationships between mean, variance, standard deviations, and medians</li>
<li>Highest Density Intervals (which, in my NHST conceptual background, are like Bayesian confidence intervals)</li>
<li>two-way probabilities, marginal probabilities, and conditional probabilities. This is where he starts to lead towards the crux of Bayes's rule.</li>
</ul>


<p>But all these things feel like sort of incomplete foreshadowing of what's to come.  Priming the pump, as it were, but I personally have a hard time retaining stuff when I don't see the point of it until later.  So again, I think in practice I would recommend zipping through and then revisiting this chapter once you've gotten into the applications later.</p>

<p>The other main way I can think to describe Kruschke's writing so far is that it is a very uneven flow of information.  There are stretches of very informal, easy-to-read text that glide by, and then I hit a sentence or two that quickly assert or review some equation or other point that is very dense, and I feel like I have to read it over several times and work through it in my head to make sure I'm understanding.  This is not really a criticism, just a description of my personal experience in reading.</p>

<p>These relatively minor worries and hand-wringings aside, I think this is a nice, concise, readable chapter.  I think he does a good job of discussing some basic concepts in probability in an extremely approachable way, in order to set up a better understanding of what's to come. It's certainly not an exhaustive treatment, but it's useful enough that I'd recommend a good reading of it, even for peole coming to the book with a decent stats background. But I really do think that most of the good points may be a little lost or unappreciated until some of the later topics in the book are broached.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reproducibility of new methods]]></title>
    <link href="http://shoestringpsycholing.github.com/blog/2012/11/04/reproducibility-of-new-methods/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-04T19:56:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://shoestringpsycholing.github.com/blog/2012/11/04/reproducibility-of-new-methods</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the main themes I'd like to talk about in this blog is the notion of <em>reproducibility</em> in research. I'll leave more in-depth discussion of the fundamental ideas for other posts; today I just want to comment on something that occurred to me while working on a paper re-submission, and I think it's also really relevant to the ongoing Bayesian stats posts as well. The issue is: <strong>new methods are inherently less reproducible</strong>.  Let me explain.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GZYhDMCOyww">No, there is too much. Let me sum up.</a></p>

<p>These days, mixed-effects models are rapidly overtaking the traditional ANOVA in some parts of the field. If the <a href="http://www.indiana.edu/~kruschke/AnOpenLetter.htm">Bayesians have their way</a> (see also <a href="http://shoestringpsycholing.github.com/blog/2012/11/02/naive-bayesian/">this post</a>), then Bayesian data analysis may make a similar sweep through my fields in another few years. But what happens when you write a paper using these shiny new methods, and either (a) your reviewers or (b) much of the audience for the paper (or both) don't understand the methods? Maybe you even include the <a href="http://www.r-project.org/">R code</a> for your analysis.  On the one hand, your analysis could be easily reproduced by anyone in the world, since R can be run for free on virtually any computer platform.  On the other hand, though, other people may find it impossible to <em>really</em> reproduce your analysis, since they don't understand it.</p>

<p>The problem is that this can cause trust to break down. Maybe the reviewers/readers decide to trust to because you seem smart and seem to know what you're doing. But in my experience, we are not trained to give people the benefit of the doubt, especially when reviewing articles for publication. The main question seems to be "why are they using this 'fancy' new method, when my old method (e.g., ANOVA) seems to work just fine?"  And even if an answer for why the new method is superior can be supplied, if it's not adequately explained, then it can't really be replicated or fully understood.</p>

<p>So what makes a method <em>really</em> reproducible?  Not just the means, but the understanding. Just as I don't expect a typical middle-schooler or even college student to be able to <em>really</em> replicate or reproduce most published analyses or results in psycholinguistics (even though they may be technically capable of re-running someone's R code), I don't expect that most psycholinguists (including myself at present) could reproduce a complex Bayesian analysis.</p>

<p>I'll leave the subtleties of this for another day, but I think it's an interesting and important issue, which I have not seen discussed explicitly, but of which I have seen (and felt!) very concrete examples.  So here's a thought: what if the future of truly reproducible research is not just "including code and data," but also including tutorials or other means to <em>educate</em> readers and reviewers? How far could or should this be pushed?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kruschke Chapter 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://shoestringpsycholing.github.com/blog/2012/11/03/kruschke-chapter-2/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-03T13:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://shoestringpsycholing.github.com/blog/2012/11/03/kruschke-chapter-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(<a href="http://shoestringpsycholing.github.com/blog/2012/11/02/naive-bayesian">Here's a link to the intro and Chapter 1 discussion</a>)</p>

<p>In this chapter, Kruschke does a nice job of succinctly laying out the primary goals of statistical inferencing, and gives a pretty clear, intuitive description of what prior and posterior beliefs are about. To paraphrase in a nutshell, prior beliefs represent our beliefs (including level of uncertainty in those beliefs) before data collection or observation, and posterior beliefs reflect what we believe after taking data into account.</p>

<p>This chapter strikes me as a nice place to do some discussions in a class about what the goals of statistics are, the idea of updating beliefs via statistics, etc.  For example, I can easily see some people being uneasy about the idea of mathematical formulas determining beliefs, in a philosophical sense. Kruschke does touch on this briefly, mentioning basically that beliefs that cannot be influenced by data are essentially "out of bounds," but he does so in kind of a flippant way. I think even if we are talking about scientific beliefs, the idea of an analysis telling you what you <em>should</em> believe (and Kruschke does use the word "should") can be uncomfortable, and not entirely realistic.</p>

<p>To clarify, in case you're new to Bayesian inference, one of the concepts behind Bayesian inference is that it gives a clear mathematical formulation for how beliefs should be changed (there's that "should" again), given the prior beliefs and the data. For example, a detective might be able to express her beliefs about suspects in terms of relative probabilities. So maybe if a woman was murdered, there could be a relatively high prior belief that it was the jealous ex-husband, and relatively low prior belief that it was the woman's 2-year-old daughter. If the detective finds the daughter's fingerprints on the murder weapon, it may only slightly affect her (nearly zero) belief that the daughter did it, where finding the husband's fingerprints may make a big difference. The point is that Bayesian inference gives a mathematical framework for actually computing how beliefs should be updated. But given what people often mean when they talk about "beliefs," the idea of a mathematical system telling you how you should change your beliefs given some data might be uncomfortable.</p>

<p>Of course, once you get a little farther, the Bayesian concept of "belief" is pretty circumscribed and clear, and it doesn't quite mean what most people mean by "belief," but I could see this point in the book being a good place for some discussion along these lines in a class. Especially because it's such a different kind of approach compared to the null-hypothesis significance testing (NHST) way of thinking about things.  If NHST is new to you, too, the NHST way of thinking about things is more that you approach a set of data and ask "what are the odds that this data occurred this way purely by chance?"  And if you decide that the odds are sufficiently low (by convention in many fields, less than 5%, or 1-in-20 odds), then you draw the conclusion that the "null hypothesis" (the hypothesis that whatever you're looking at happened just by chance) is probably false. This comes up more directly later in the book, but that's the gist, if all this stats stuff is new to you.</p>

<p>But back to the three goals as Kruschke presents them: (1) estimation of parameter values, (2) prediction of data values, and (3) model comparison.  Depending on the context of who's reading this book, I could see the benefit of some more examples of these things, but the presentation in the text is nice and clear.  Kruschke makes an interesting point about Bayesian analysis "intrinsically adjust[ing] for model complexity" (p. 14), but the significance of this is likely to be lost on anyone not familiar with model comparison in other (e.g., NHST) methods. In terms of the audience of the book, I think these points will be much more interesting and meaningful to anyone who's actually done data analysis before, and they may fly right by someone who's relatively new to it.</p>

<p>Finally, Kruschke includes a short intro to the <a href="http://www.r-project.org/">R software and programming language</a>. There's not really a great way to introduce R in 7 pages, but Kruschke does a decent job of giving the minimum needed to help people get the ball rolling.  Again, here's another spot where his <a href="http://www.indiana.edu/~kruschke/DoingBayesianDataAnalysis/">website</a> outpaces the book already, because the website makes the excellent recommendation of using <a href="http://www.rstudio.org/">RStudio</a>, instead of the (IMHO) inferior  <a href="http://www.sciviews.org/Tinn-R/">Tinn-R</a>. No knock against the fine folks who put together Tinn-R.  This is just one of those things that makes it hard to write static books about R.  RStudio is a pretty new player in the GUI game, but it's quickly become the favorite for general users for a lot of good reasons.  In any case, Kruschke will not make you an expert at R. But he gives you enough to run through the code in the book, cookbook-style. I suspect for anyone needing to work with real data, some additional resources or expertise in R will be needed to go from raw data to Bayesian analysis. <strong>R pet peeve alert:</strong> throughout the book, Kruschke uses the style of using <code>=</code> instead of <code>&lt;-</code> for assignment. This may help many people coming from other programming languages, but it's a little non-idiomatic for R.  But this is a pretty inconsequential pet peeve, and since the book is about Bayesian analysis, not R coding style, I think overall this is not a bad choice.</p>

<p>In summary, it's a good chapter and covers a bunch of introductory bases.  Depending on who's reading the book, and what the goals are (class textbook vs. self-study), a good amount of supplementary material or discussion could be useful, or it could be fine to just skim this chapter to get on to the meatier stuff.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Naive Bayesian]]></title>
    <link href="http://shoestringpsycholing.github.com/blog/2012/11/02/naive-bayesian/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-02T07:04:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://shoestringpsycholing.github.com/blog/2012/11/02/naive-bayesian</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Huh?</h2>

<p>A big part of my day-to-day involves data analysis, usually statistical data analysis. The stats scene has been in some flux lately, at least in the fields I work in, and interestingly, I think a lot of that has resulted, directly or indirectly, from the availability of the <a href="http://www.r-project.org/">R statistical language/package</a>. Long story short, it has increased accessibility to methods that are not all that new in the scheme of things, but which have not been terribly accessible.  More on all that another day.</p>

<p>Today, the topic is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Bayes">Bayesian</a> stats. The word "Bayesian" is a bit of a buzz-word for a wide range of different topics in computational and statistical work, but despite this, it's a really important modern approach to data and analysis.  What exactly is it, and what's the big deal?  Damned if I know, but in an ongoing series of posts, I intend to find out a lot more, and share my thoughts here.</p>

<p>So here's the idea:  starting virtually from scratch, I'm going to walk through a recent <a href="http://www.indiana.edu/~kruschke/DoingBayesianDataAnalysis/">book</a> by <a href="http://www.indiana.edu/~kruschke/">John Kruschke</a>, and give my own knee-jerk reactions, as a kind of extended review of the book, and the usefulness of Bayesian methods for language scientists (and maybe others). Kruschke himself is a very um... <em>outspoken</em> advocate of Bayesian analysis (see this <a href="http://www.indiana.edu/~kruschke/AnOpenLetter.htm">"Open Letter"</a>), and while I'm generally pretty sympathetic and find most of these arguments pretty convincing, I'll try to take a skeptical stance when going through the book.</p>

<p>My own stats background is pretty hodge-podgy, but I can hold my own in comparison to most folks in my field. My hope is that by going through the book in this way, I'll get more out of the book myself, and it might help other folks decide whether looking into Bayesian stats could be worth their time, too.  Big props go to Amber Springer for getting a local reading group started on this book. I wasn't able to attend as much as I'd have liked to, but going to a couple of meetings really got the ball rolling for me, and I appreciate it!</p>

<h2>The Big Deal, in a nutshell</h2>

<p>If all this is utterly mysterious and the word "Bayesian" might as well be "Martian," here's the basic gist of why I'm spending time on this. "Traditional" stats in the fields I work in are more or less descended from seminal work by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ronald_Fisher">Ronald Fisher</a> and others, and can also be referred to as "Null Hypothesis Significance Testing." If you've ever looked for a "p-value" to tell you if your experiment "worked," this is the framework you're used to. It boils down to a system of making inferences based on data, because that's ultimately what we want, to look at data and have it tell us something so we can make inferential conclusions.  Like looking at language learning outcome measures and using those to tell you whether Teaching Method A was more effective than Teaching Method B. Or whatever.</p>

<p>The point made by folks like Kruschke is quite simply that the NHST system of making inferences is broken, and we need to switch to Bayesian methods, which involves a different system of making inferences from data. There has been quite the war within the field of statistics, with both sides (NHST and Bayesian) attacking the other program as obviously wrong and utterly misguided. My impression is that this polemic has faded a little, and other folks, like <a href="http://andrewgelman.com/">Andrew Gelman</a>, are not quite as divisive, but they often claim that Bayesian methods have distinct advantages over NHST methods. Wanting to understand what those advantages might be, and whether they could help with the sometimes very sticky data analysis situations I find myself in, are my main motivations.</p>

<p>That, and trying to understand what <a href="http://www.nhsilbert.net/">Noah Silbert</a> is going on about half the time.</p>

<p>So without further ado, I'm just going to launch into each chapter, throwing out my reactions and thoughts.</p>

<h2>Chapter 1</h2>

<p>This is a very short chapter, but a nice one to have.  It walks you through the structure of the book, and tries to assuage your fears that this book might be too much for you. In terms of prerequisites, Kruschke says that you don't really need any programming experience, and as long as you have a "dim knowledge of basic calculus," you should be fine.  I'm pretty sure my R skills will be up to snuff, but I will be a good test for his claims about calculus.  My knowledge (specifically, my memory of calculus from my high school course um... 18(!) years ago) is about as dim as it gets.  This chapter also gets you an intro to Kruschke's writing style, which is pretty goofy.  I mean that in a good way, though.  It's very conversational, and peppered with plenty of corny humor.  I imagine Kruschke's students groaning a lot (maybe on the inside, if they're respectful) in class, but staying awake because of it, and I suspect this will play out similarly in the book. I think this is probably a good thing, but we'll see.</p>

<p>One note, I didn't do an exhaustive search, but Kruschke gives HTTP addresses for both the Elsevier site and his personal site, and it looks like his personal site is where you should go to get programs, etc.  It's a little more scattered, visually, but his site is much more complete, and looks like it has a bunch of updated versions of programs, exercises, etc., where the Elsevier site has the more "basic" version of the code.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
